# Valentina Roquemen-Echeverri

roquemev@ohsu.edu

in linkedin.com/in/valentina-roquemen-echeverri/

https://valentina-roquemenecheverri.netlify.app

## Summary

√ Algorithms and data scientist with 3+ years combined academic and industry experience in signal processing, statistical analysis, and ML modeling.

√ Proficient in the use of data science and ML development tools (e.g., Pandas, SciPy, Scikit-learn, TensorFlow, and PvTorch).

✓ Enthusiastic about communicating complex concepts effectively.

## **Experience**

March 2022 - Present

**Graduate researcher (current)** Oregon Health & Science University.

✓ Developed a first-of-its-kind explainable neural ODE digital twin framework in diabetes, using state space neural networks formally verified to be conformant with physiology, enabling accurate and personalized in-silico pre-clinical testing of diabetes technologies. Achieving and increase of the accuracy of 21% compared against mechanistic model (♂ see GitHub).

✓ Analyzed an evidential neural network using explainable AI (SHAP) to study factors associated with increased risk of nocturnal hypoglycemia in type 1 diabetes.

✓ Performed processing and statistical analysis of data collected during clinical studies and disseminated research results through two peer-reviewed journal articles (see Google Scholar 🗷 ) and presentations at top diabetes focused conference.

✓ Mentored two high school interns in the lab in performing automated literature reviews and data analysis.

April 2021 - Nov 2021

Auxiliar control gestion CNV construcciones.

✓ Developed an algorithm to automatically process emails describing construction tenders according to relevance.

## **Education**

Ph.D. C, Biomedical Engineering 4.0/4.0 GPA 2022 -

Oregon Health & Science University, Portland, USA

**B.Sc.**, Physics 4.46/5.0 GPA 2015-2021

Universidad de Antioquia, Medellín, COL

#### Technical Skills

Technical specialities Computational biology, data analysis, applied machine learning, signal processing

Programming and scripting Python, C++, R, Bash

Data analysis and machine learning Pandas, Tensorflow, Scikit-learn, pyTorch

> Operating systems Linux, macOS, Microsoft Windows.

Version control systems.

Languages English (professional proficiency), Spanish (native)

#### **Honors and Awards**

Reviewer of the month, Journal of Medical Artificial Intelligence see JMAI 2. 2024

OHSU School of Medicine article of the month, (see Mosquera-Lopez et al., Computers in Biology 2023 and Medicine, 2023) ♂.

WIS Professional developments scholarship, Women in Science PDX see WISPDX Blog 2. 2022

Bachelor's thesis with honors, Universidad de Antioquia. 2021

Best advanced student in the physics program, Universidad de Antioquia. 2020

Dean's list, Universidad de Antioquia. 2017-2019